My name's Conan Edogawa.
اسمي إيدوغاوا كونان
High school student Shinichi was forced to take a drug that shrunk him.
أُجبر طالب الثانوية شينتشي على تجرّع عقار قلّص جسده
Although smaller, my intelligence remains the same!
رغم صغر بنيتي، لا يزال عقلي كما هو
I solve cases not even adults can!
!أحلّ قضايا تستعصي حتى على البالغين
Sorry for the wait! Today's Conan is a one-hour special!
!نعتذر على التأخير! حلقة اليوم هي حلقة خاصة بساعة كاملة
The Piano Sonata "Moonlight" Murders.
!وحقيقة سوناتا البيانو الحزينة
Why does the famous detective Kogoro Mori have to go to a stupid island
يا إلهي، لمَ على المتحري الشهير موري كوغورو الذهاب لجزيرة سخيفة
when he could be spending his time at a flower viewing party?!
بينما يمكنه قضاء وقته في حفلة مشاهدة أزهار؟
It's all because of that letter I got a week ago!
كلّ هذا بسبب الرسالة التي وصلتني قبل أسبوع
On the night of the next full moon,
،في ليلة البدر التالي
shadows will once again begin to disappear from Tsukikage Island.
ستبدأ الظلال بالاختفاء مُجدداً من جزيرة تسوكيكاغي
Investigate. Keiji Aso.
تحرَّ. أسو كيجي
Mori Detective Agency.
أجل، وكالة موري للتحري
Two days until the next full moon.
تبقى يومان حتّى البدر التالي
I've transferred half a million to your bank account.
حوّلتُ نصف مليون لحسابك البنكي
You had best come.
عليك أن تأتي
Hold on! Who the heck are you?!
!لـ-لحظة! من أنت؟
Keiji Aso from Tsukikage Island.
أسو كيجي من جزيرة تسوكيكاغي
Hey, wait! Hello?!
!أنت! انتظر! أتسمعني؟ مرحباً؟
He didn't even bother for me to accept him as a client or not!
يا إلهي، لم يهتم لقبولي طلبه من عدمه حتى
What's to complain about?
أين المشكلة؟
At least we get to relax on a small island near Izu!
يمكننا الاسترخاء في جزيرة صغيرة قرب إيزو
Right, Conan-kun?
صحيح يا كونان-كن؟
Tsukikage Island
جزيرة تسوكيكاغي
Keiji Aso...
...أسو كيجي
I don't see anyone by that name in here...
لا أرى شخصاً بهذا الاسم هنا
Look harder, could you?!
هلّا بحثت جيّداً؟
I have a letter from him right here, after all...
فقد استلمتُ رسالةً منه
But he's not in the list of residents,
لكنه ليس في لائحة السكان
and I just moved to this island, so I don't know that much about--
وأنا انتقلتُ لهذه الجزيرة مؤخراً، فلا أعرف الكثير
Is something the matter?
أهناك خطبٌ ما؟
Chief, it seems that these people have been hired by a resident here...
رئيس، يبدو أنّ ساكناً هنا عيّن هؤلاء الأشخاص في عمل
Hired?
عيّن؟
That's right. By someone named Keiji Aso...
أجل، اسمه أسو كيجي
What? Did you say Keiji Aso?!
!ماذا؟ أقلت أسو كيجي؟
That's not possible! He's been dead for over 10 years!
!ذلك مُحال! فهو ميت منذ أكثر من 10 سنوات
He was a famous pianist who was born and raised on this island.
كان عازف بيانو مشهور وُلد وترعرع في هذه الجزيرة
It was the night of a full moon, 12 years ago...
وقعت الحادثة في ليلة بدر قبل 12 عاماً
It was his first time home in a long time,
كانت أول مرة يعود لموطنه منذ وقت طويل
so he held a concert in the town's community center.
فأقام حفلةً في مركز البلدة الاجتماعي
But afterwards, he suddenly shut his family and himself inside their home
لكن بعدها، أقفل على نفسه وعائلته في منزلهم فجأةً
and lit the place on fire!
!وأحرق المكان
He allegedly stabbed his wife and daughter to death
قِيل أنّه طعن زوجته وابنته حتى الموت
and then continued to play the piano as the fire raged on,
ثمّ واصل العزف بالبيانو وألسنة اللهب تحيطه
almost as if he was possessed by something.
كما لو كان هناك شيء يتلبسه
Beethoven's piano sonata... "Moonlight."
"سوناتا البيانو لبيتهوفين... "ضوء القمر
A letter from a dead man...
...رسالة من رجل ميت
What a nasty prank.
يا للمقلب الفظيع
That's not necessarily the case.
قد لا يكون كذلك
Your fee was paid, plus the letter was postmarked from this island.
فأجرك قد دُفع، كما أنّ الرسالة حملت خاتم بريد هذه الجزيرة
I bet someone on the island wants you to look into Keiji Aso's affairs!
يريد أحد أهل الجزيرة منك التحري في أمر أسو كيجي حتماً
He's right!
صحيح
The mayor here used to be a good friend of his,
كان العمدة هنا صديقاً مقرّباً منه
maybe he can tell us something!
فربما يمكنه إخبارنا بشيء
Yeah...
صحيح
They said the mayor's over at the community center, right?
قالوا أنّ العمدة في المركز الاجتماعي، أليس كذلك؟
Now then, Kenta-kun. Make sure to keep warm when you sleep.
اسمع يا كينتا-كن، احرص على أن تنام بدفء
Okay, I will! Bye!
!أجل، فهمت! إلى اللقاء
Bye!
مع السلامة
Excuse me!
المعذرة
Where is the community center?
أين المركز الاجتماعي؟
You turn that corner and then keep going straight.
أجل، اسلكوا ذاك المنعطف ثمّ واصلوا المشي
Wait, are you folks from Tokyo?!
لحظة، هل أنتم الجماعة من طوكيو؟
That's right. We got off the ship just now.
أجل، وصلنا من السفينة للتو
I live in Tokyo too!
!أنا من طوكيو أيضاً
But this island is so much nicer, wouldn't you agree?
لكن هذه الجزيرة أروع بكثير، ألا تتفقون؟
The air's fresh, and it's nice and quiet!
!الهواء منعش، وهي هادئة جداً
Protect the island's fishing industry! Vote for Masato Shimizu!
!احموا تجارة الصيد للجزيرة! صوّتوا لشيميزو ماساتو
Well, maybe not too quiet.
ربما ليس كثيراً
The mayoral election is coming up, you see.
فانتخابات العمدة تقترب
The mayoral election, huh?
انتخابات العمدة؟
The candidates are Shimizu-san, who represents the fishermen,
المرشّحون هم شيميزو-سان الذي يمثل صيّادي السمك
current mayor Kuroiwa-san, whose popularity is dwindling as of late,
والعمدة الحالي الذي يعاني انخفاضاً في شعبيته مؤخراً، كوريوا-سان
and Kawashima-san, the wealthiest man on the island.
كما كاواشيما-سان، أكثر رجال الجزيرة ثراءً
My patients have been telling me that Kawashima-san will probably--
...أخبرني مرضاي أنّ كاواشيما-سان غالباً مَن
That's alright, Nurse. We're not really that interested in the election...
لا بأس يا ممرضة، لسنا مهتمين بالانتخابات حقاً
That's Doctor Narumi Asai.
أنا الطبيبة أساي نارومي
I have an actual license, you know!
!لديّ رخصة حقيقية
Oh, you're a doctor...
كنتِ دكتورة إذاً
If you folks are headed to the community center,
إن كنتم متجهين للمركز الاجتماعي
you can meet the three of them there!
فيمكنكم لقاء أولئك الثلاثة هناك
Tonight they're holding a 3rd-year memorial for Kameyama-san,
فستُعقد الليلة مناسبة ذكرى العام الثالث للعمدة السابق
our previous mayor.
كامياما-سان
Your previous mayor?
العمدة السابق؟
A 3rd-year memorial?
ذكرى العام الثالث؟
Don't let the mayor continue his reign of terror!
!لا تدعوا العمدة يواصل حكم إرهابه
Give me a break.
يا إلهي
How dare they do this on the night of the previous mayor's memorial?!
كيف يجرؤون على فعل هذا في !ليلة ذكرى العمدة السابق؟ يا لوقاحتهم
They're really getting on my nerves!
إنّهم مزعجون حقاً
Hirata! What're you doing?! Shut them up already!
!هيراتا! ما الذي تفعله؟ !أغلق أفواههم فوراً
Yes, ma'am!
!حاضر سيّدتي
Don't let the mayor continue his reign of terror!
!لا تدعوا العمدة يواصل حكم إرهابه
Hey, everything okay?
هل الأمور بخير؟
Is what okay, Shuichi?
ما قصدك يا شويتشي؟
They're saying this election ain't looking so good for your old man.
يقولون أنّ الانتخابات المقبلة لن تكون في صالح والدك
Indeed. It would seem the citizens favor me the most.
فعلاً، يبدو أنّ المواطنين يميلون لي الأكثر بينكم
That's only because you know how to use money.
هذا لأنّك تعرف كيف تستعمل المال فقط
Which I learned from you, of course.
ما تعلّمتُه منك بالطبع
There's a man here who wants to see the mayor!
يوجد رجل يريد رؤية العمدة
Who is it, at a time like this?!
من يكون في وقت كهذا؟
A detective from Tokyo...
...مُتحرٍّ من طوكيو
What? A detective?!
!ماذا؟ مُتحرٍّ؟
Come on, how long are they going to make me wait?!
يا إلهي، إلى متى سيجعلونني أنتظر؟
Huh? Where's Conan-kun?
ماذا؟ أين كونان-كن؟
A piano...
بيانو؟
Stop that, Conan-kun!
!كونان-كن! توقف
Huh? What a huge room!
!ماذا؟ يا للغرفة الكبيرة
So the rear of the community center is on the water's edge...
طرف الشاطئ على الجانب الخلفي تماماً للمركز الاجتماعي إذاً
This piano sure is dirty...
هذا البيانو متسخ
You'd think they could at least clean it once in a while...
...بمقدورهم تنظيفه بين الحين والآخر على الأقل
No, don't touch that!
!كلا! لا تلمسيه
That's the cursed piano that Aso-san played the day he died!
!إنّه البيانو الملعون الذي عزف أسو-سان عليه يوم موته
Cursed? Give me a break...
...ملعون؟ لا تبالغ
Aso-san wasn't the only one!
لم يكن أسو-سان الوحيد
The same thing happened to the last mayor!
!حلّ الأمر نفسه بالعمدة السابق
You mean Isamu Kameyama-san,
،تقصد كامياما إيسامو-سان
the person they're holding the memorial for today?
الذي يعقدون تذكاراً له اليوم؟
Yes. It happened 2 years ago.
أجل، حدث الأمر قبل عامين
It was the night of a full moon.
كانت ليلة بدر
I was passing by the community center, which should have been empty,
كنتُ أمرّ بالمركز الاجتماعي الذي يفترض أنّ لا أحد به
when I heard the sounds of a piano coming from inside.
حين سمعت صوت عزف بيانو من الداخل
When I called out to see who was there, the music stopped.
عندما سألتُ إن كان هناك أحد، توقف العزف
Inside, I found Kameyama-san!
!وفي الداخل، وجدت كامياما-ساما
He had died of a heart attack.
مات من نوبة قلبية
And the music he had been playing before he died
والمقطوعة التي كان يعزفها قبيل موته
was the same piece Aso-san had performed in the fire: "Moonlight."
"كانت نفس التي عزفها أسو-سان داخل النار، "ضوء القمر
After that, this piano came to be known as the Cursed Piano.
بعدها أصبح هذا البيانو معروفاً بالبيانو الملعون
Conan-kun!
!كونان-كن
Seems normal enough to me.
لا أرى خطباً غريباً بهذا البيانو
Anyway, please wait by the front door until the memorial is over!
بأيّ حال، انتظروا عند الباب الأمامي لحين !انتهاء المناسبة التذكارية رجاءً
Oh, you're still here?
لا تزالون هنا؟
Narumi-san! Are you going to the memorial?
نارومي-سان، أستحضرين المناسبة؟
Yes. Kameyama-san was the first person I autopsied when I came here.
أجل، كان كامياما-سان أوّل من شرّحته عندما أتيت هنا
I thought I would burn some incense in his honor.
لذا خطر لي أن أحرق بخوراً لتكريمه
Oh, this is Shimizu-san. I happened to meet him on the way.
هذا شيميزو-سان، التقيته في طريقي
Hey, Kawashima.
كاواشيما
You hired a detective to dig up some dirt on me, didn't you?!
عيّنت مُتحرياً للتنقيب عن أسراري، صحيح؟
Don't be stupid.
سخافة
Running away?!
!تهرب؟
Bathroom.
الحمّام
It's strange.
هذا غريب
That piano should have remained unused for years now,
يُفترض أن ذاك البيانو غير مستعمل لأعوام
but it produced a perfect sound.
لكنه أصدر صوتاً مثالياً
Someone must be tuning it secretly.
كان أحدهم يضبطه سرّاً بالتأكيد
For some purpose...
...لغرض ما
And what exactly was that letter trying to say?
وما كان معنى تلك الرسالة بالتحديد؟
This song!
!هـ-هذه المعزوفة
...Moonlight! Oh no!
!ضوء القمر! كلا
Conan-kun!
!كونان-كن
Hey! Little boy!
!أنت! أيها الصبي
It's Kawashima-san!
!كاواشيما-سان
Too late!
!تأخرت
He's dead.
إنّه ميت
What?!
!ماذا؟
Ran. Contact the local police station!
ران، اتّصلي بمركز الشرطة المحلي
Right!
!حسناً
Dr. Narumi. Please inspect the body.
طبيبة نارومي، افحصي الجثة رجاءً
Right.
حسناً
Now I see!
هكذا إذاً
That letter warned that another person on Tsukikage Island
حذّرتنا تلك الرسالة من موت شخص مرّة أخرى في جزيرة تسوكيكاغي
would die on the night of a full moon!
!في ليلة بدر
It's the curse! It's the curse of the piano!
!إ-إنها اللعنة! إنها لعنة البيانو
There's no curse. It's this tape recorder that's playing the music.
لا لعنة هناك، هذا المسجّل هو ما يشغل الموسيقى
This was a murder designed to resemble the previous two incidents!
!هذه جريمة قتل أُعدّت لتشبه الحادثتين السابقتين
Murder?!
!جريمة قتل؟
Hey now, don't be getting ahead of yourself.
أنت، لا تتفوه بالهراء
Who the hell are you, anyway?!
!من تكون بالأصل؟
I'm a famous detective from Tokyo-- Kogoro Mori!
!أنا المتحرّي الشهير من طوكيو، موري كوغورو
Oh, the astronaut?
رائد الفضاء ذاك؟
No, he's the one in all those mystery novels.
كلا، إنّه من يظهر في روايات التحرّي
That's Akechi.
ذاك أكيتشي
Then who's this?
من يكون هذا الشخص إذاً؟
Seawater.
ماء بحر
Approximate time of death was 30 minutes to an hour ago.
وقت الموت المقدر هو قبل نصف ساعة لساعة
He probably died of suffocation.
مات اختناقاً غالباً
My guess is that Kawashima-san drowned.
أعتقد أنّ كاواشيما-سان قد أُغرق
Drowned by someone?
أغرقه أحدهم؟
I can't say any more without performing an autopsy.
لا يمكنني الجزم دون إجراء تشريح
I think Dr. Narumi is right.
أظنّ الطبيبة نارومي محقّة
See, there's a suit jacket on the beach outside.
انظروا، يوجد معطف بدلة على الشاطئ خارجاً
I bet it belongs to Kawashima-san.
لا بد أنّه لكاواشيما-سان
There's a trail of water here that goes from the door to the piano
يوجد أثر ماء بحر يمتد من الباب للبيانو
and there's mud and sand on Kawashima-san's back.
وهناك وحل ورمل على ظهر كاواشيما-سان
And judging from the fact that the door and windows were all locked,
،كما من كون باب ونوافذ هذه الغرفة مغلقة
and that the first few minutes of the cassette tape are blank...
...وفراغ الدقائق الأولى من شريط المسجّل
When did he become so...?
...مـ-منذ متى بدأ
The killer probably took Kawashima-san to the ocean during the memorial,
أخذ المجرم كاواشيما-سان للمحيط أثناء المناسبة التذكارية غالباً
drowned him,
وأغرقه
dragged the body into this room,
ثمّ سحب الجثّة لهذه الغرفة
locked the door,
أقفل الباب
turned the tape recorder on, and then exited into the hallway.
شغّل مسجّل الأشرطة ثم خرج للرواق
Right?
صحيح يا عمّ؟
Y-Yeah, sounds about right to me!
أ-أجل، معك حق
Assuming the door to this room was locked,
بافتراض أنّ باب هذه الغرفة كان مقفلاً
there's a high possibility the killer returned to the memorial afterwards,
،هناك احتمال كبير أن القاتل رجع لقاعة المناسبة
since we were at the front door the whole time!
بما أنّنا كنا عند الباب الأمامي طوال الوقت
Hold on just a second!
!ا-انتظر
Are you saying the killer's still among us?!
!أتقصد أن القاتل لا يزال بيننا؟
Yes, the killer is in this very room.
صحيح، المجرم هنا
Did anyone here see Kawashima-san leave his seat?
هل رأى أحدكم كاواشيما-سان يترك مقعده؟
I saw him. He said he was going to the restroom.
أنا رأيته، قال أنه سيذهب للحمّام
Did anybody see anyone else leave their seat?
هل رأى أحدكم شخصاً آخر غادر مقعده؟
As if we could remember every little thing that happened.
كأن بإمكاننا تذكر كلّ تفصيل حدث
In that case, did anyone have any grudges with Kawashima-san?
في هذه الحالة، أكان يحمل أحد ضغينة ضدّ كاواشيما-سان؟
It's not exactly a grudge,
ليست ضغينة تماماً
but the person most happy about his death would be Shimizu-kun,
،لكن أكثر شخص سيسرّ بموته هو شيميزو-سان
his opponent in the mayoral election!
خصمه في انتخابات العمدة
What?! The same goes for you, Mayor Kuroiwa!
!مـ-ماذا؟! ينطبق الأمر عليك يا عمدة كوريوا
Yes, without Kawashima-san,
أجل، دون كاواشيما-سان
Daddy's victory would practically be guaranteed!
كان نصر أبي ليكون مضموناً
As long as a certain someone
طالما لم يكن أحدهم يخطط
wasn't plotting to steal Kawashima-san's votes, of course.
لسرقة أصوات كاواشيما-سان بالطبع
What?!
!ماذا؟
Now, now, there!
!سيّدتي
Calm down now...
...اهدؤوا
But why did the killer put the body in this room?
لكن لمَ وضع القاتلُ الجثّةَ في هذه الغرفة؟
Because the killer wanted to place the blame on the cursed piano.
ذلك لأنّ القاتل أراد توجيه اللوم للبيانو الملعون
Say, just how long has this piano been here?
بالمناسبة، منذ متى والبيانو هنا؟
It's been here ever since Aso-san donated it 15 years ago.
كان هنا لخمسة عشر عاماً مذ تبرع به أسو-سان
Aso-san, eh?
أسو-سان ذاك إذاً؟
Yes. His name is even on the keyboard lid.
أجل، اسمه على غطاء لوحة المفاتيح حتى
What's this?
ما-ما هذا؟
It's sheet music.
قطعة موسيقية
That's strange. This wasn't here when we checked this afternoon.
غريب، لم تكن موجودةً عندما تفقدناه في الظهيرة
Who was that?
من كان ذاك؟
Nishimoto-san.
نيشيموتو-سان
He did rather well for himself back in the day.
كان بحالٍ ممتازة في السابق
I hear he spent lots of money on alcohol, women, and gambling...
وأنفق الكثير من المال على الشراب والنساء والقمار كما سمعت
But after the mayor died 2 years ago,
،لكن بعد موت العمدة قبل عامين
he stopped going out, almost as if he were afraid of something.
توقف عن الخروج كما لو كان يخشى شيئاً
I see.
هكذا إذاً
Wasn't he a childhood friend of yours, Mayor?
كان صديق طفولة لك أيها العمدة، صحيح؟
Yes, I suppose you could say that...
أ-أجل، معك حق
Here's a policeman!
!إنّه شرطي
You're late, Ran!
تأخّرتِ يا ران
But I had to look for him, he wasn't at the police station!
لكن كان عليّ البحث عنه، لم يكن في مركز الشرطة
Who called for me now?
حسناً، من طلبني؟
This gentleman here. His name is Kogoro Mori.
هذا الشخص، اسمه موري كوغورو
Oh, the famous--
...ذاك المشهور
That's right!
!أجل
Astronaut!
!رائد الفضاء
No...
...كلا
At any rate, it's getting late.
بأيّ حال، تأخر الوقت
We can put off collecting information until tomorrow morning.
يمكننا تأجيل جمع المعلومات لصباح الغد
This was no murder. It was Aso-san's curse.
لم تكن جريمة قتل، كانت لعنة أسو-سان
How horrifying...
...يا للرعب
They should just burn that creepy old piano!
كان عليهم حرق ذاك البيانو القديم المريب
Yeah. Maybe we'd be better off without that thing.
أجل، قد نكون أفضل حالاً دون ذاك الشيء
Shuichi?
شويتشي؟
Your deductions sure surprised me, Conan-kun!
!أدهشتني استنتاجاتك يا كونان-كن
He loves playing detective!
يحب لعب لعبة المُتحري
Everyone was talking about how amazing his persuasiveness was!
كان الجميع يتكلمون عن قوّة إقناعه
I was just pretending to be like Detective Kogoro!
!كنتُ أقلد عمّي فقط
I always get to see him at work!
!فأنا أراه في عمله دوماً
He's just a baby chick compared to me, though!
لكنّه مجرد فرخ مقارنةً بي
Well, we'll head back to the hotel now.
حسنٌ، سنرجع للنُزل الآن
I'll see you later then. Please solve this case as quickly as possible.
أراكم لاحقاً إذاً، آمل أن تحلّ القضية بأسرع ما يمكن
I'd rather not have to examine any more bodies.
أفضّل ألا أفحص جثثاً أكثر
Don't you worry! This'll be a piece of cake with me at the helm!
!لا تقلقي! سيكون هذا لقمةً سائغة بين يديّ
Whatever. Not even I really know what's going on yet...
يا للادّعاء، حتّى أنا لا أعرف ما يجري
Wait a second!
لحظة
That letter said, "begin to disappear"...
..."قالت الرسالة "ستبدأ بالاختفاء
Meaning this isn't over yet!
!أي أنّ هذه ليست النهاية
What? This murder spree has yet to continue?
!ماذا؟ لن تتوقف جرائم القتل؟
This letter gives warning about that?
هذه الرسالة تحذرنا من ذلك؟
"Shadows disappearing" means "being enveloped by light."
اختفاء الظلال يعني تطويق الضوء لها
Light stands for the song played at all the murder scenes--Moonlight!
يرمز الضوء للمقطوعة في كل المسارح الجريمة، ضوء القمر
Now I see!
!فهمت
The song Mr. Aso played in the fire 12 years ago...
المقطوعة التي عزفها السيّد أسو بين ،ألسنة النار قبل 12 عاماً
And the song the mayor played before he died 2 years ago...
والتي عزفها العمدة قبل وفاته منذ عامين
It was Beethoven's piano sonata, Moonlight.
كانت سوناتا بيانو بيتهوفين، ضوء القمر
And all three incidents have taken place beside the piano.
وكلّ الحوادث الثلاث وقعت بجوار البيانو
You two go back to the hotel!
!ارجعا للنُزل
Wait!
!انتظر
Ran! Let's go to the community center too!
!لنذهب يا ران-نيتشان للمركز الاجتماعي أيضاً
You're crazy if you ask me.
أنتَ لست بعقلك حقاً
Spending a night with a corpse like this...
تقضي الليلة مع جثّة هكذا
And with a kid, too!
!كما مع طفل
I thought I told you to go back!
!أخبرتكما أن ترجعا
But Conan-kun...
...لكن كونان-كن
Tell me, who moved the body without permission?
أخبرني، من حرّك الجثة دون إذني؟
Me.
أنا
I felt bad for the poor guy, being stuck in that position...
شعرت بالأسف للمسكين في وضعيته
You really shouldn't have,
هذه مشكلة
we're not through investigating the crime scene yet...
لم ننته من التحقيق في مسرح الجريمة بعد
Huh? The sheet music's gone.
ماذا؟ اختفت القطعة الموسيقية
What?!
!ماذا؟
Oh, I took that so it wouldn't get lost. See?
أخذتها معي كيلا تضيع، انظر
Stupid old geezer...
...هذا العجوز
Huh?
ماذا؟
This sheet music is for Moonlight!
!هذه مقطوعة ضوء القمر
What?!
!ماذا؟
Moonlight?!
ضوء القمر؟
What're you doing? You suck!
!ما الذي تفعلينه؟! فاشلة العزف
No, this fourth bar is weird...
كلا، هذه الفاصلة الرابعة غريبة
Maybe this sheet music is actually...
...أيمكن أنّ هذه القطعة الموسيقية
...Kawashima-san's dying message...
رسالة احتضار كاواشيما-سان؟
If so, then the killer might come back for it!
!في تلك الحالة، قد يرجع القاتل لها
Pardon me...
المعذرة
When I asked for you at the hotel, they said you were all here...
عندما سألت عنكم في النُزل قالوا أنّكم هنا
Dr. Narumi...
الطبيبة نارومي
I brought some dinner.
أحضرتُ عشاءً
Come to think of it...
...صحيح
...we could use some food...
نتضور جوعاً
So you're not originally from this island then, Dr. Narumi?
لستِ من أهل الجزيرة إذاً؟
No. I return to Tokyo on the weekends.
كلا، أعود لطوكيو نهاية كلّ أسبوع
It's almost like I work as a part-time doctor here!
كأنّي أعمل طبيبة بدوام جزئي هنا
I've always wanted to work on a small island like this,
،لطالما أردت أن أعمل في جزيرة صغيرة كهذه
surrounded by nature...
...محاطةً بالطبيعة
I've been working here for 2 years now!
أكملت عامين هذه السنة
Dr. Narumi.
الطبيبة نارومي
Did Mayor Kameyama really die of a heart attack two years ago?
هل مات العمدة السابق كامياما من نوبة قلبية قبل عامين حقاً؟
Yes. He had always had heart troubles...
أجل، كان يعاني مشاكل قلبية باستمرار
But his face looked rather convulsive,
لكن كان وجهه متشنّجاً
almost as if he saw something horrifying...
كما لو رأى شيئاً مرعباً
Did you notice anything strange at the time?
هل لاحظتِ أمراً غريباً آنذاك؟
Hmm, now that you mention it...
حسناً... تذكرت
What?
ماذا؟
I think one of the windows was open.
أظن أن إحدى النوافذ كانت مفتوحة
A window?
نافذة؟
I believe we chalked that up to someone forgetting to close it, but...
...اعتقدنا أن أحداً نسي إغلاقها فقط آنذاك، لكن
Which window was it?
أيّ نافذة كانت؟
If I remember right...
...وفقما أتذكر
...it was this window.
كانت هذه النافذة
Who's there?!
!من هناك؟
Stop!
!توقف
You're not getting away!
!لن تهرب
Damn it! We lost him!
!تبّاً! فقدناه
I was right! He did come back to get this sheet music!
كنتُ محقاً! رجع لأخذ هذه القطعة الموسيقية
Okay! We're going to stay up all night and keep watch over this place!
!حسنٌ! سنسهر طوال الليلة ونحرس المكان
Agreed?!
!واضح؟
Agreed!
!أجل
Hey. Mori-kun.
أنت، موري-كن
Mori-kun!
!موري-كن
It's afternoon.
إنّها الظهيرة
Inspector Megure-dono... What are you doing here?
حضرة المفتش ميغوري، ماذا تفعل هنا؟
This island's technically part of Tokyo.
هذه الجزيرة تعتبر جزءاً من طوكيو
Oh, yeah. Where did I put it?
صحيح، أين وضعت تلك؟
If you're looking for the sheet music, Conan-kun gave it to me.
،إن كنت تقصد القطعة الموسيقية فكونان-كن أعطاني إياها
He also gave me the gist of the situation here.
شرح لي تفاصيل الوضع أيضاً
All three of them were still awake by the time I arrived.
كان ثلاثتهم مستيقظين عند وصولنا
You and that old man were the only ones asleep.
أنت وذاك العجوز كنتما وحدكما النائمين
They're interrogating people over at the town hall.
إنّهم يجرون استجوابات في دار البلدية
Come give them a hand.
اذهب وساعدهم
Sure...
حسناً
We really shouldn't have slept there...
كان علينا ألّا ننام هناك
Dad! Well? Did you figure out who did it?
أبي، كيف جرى الأمر؟ هل عرفت المجرم؟
Yeah, right. There were 38 people at the memorial.
لا تكوني سخيفة، كان هناك 38 شخصاً في المناسبة التذكارية
It won't be that easy.
لن يكون الأمر بتلك السهولة
Sorry, but when will it be my turn?
آسفة، لكن متى سيحين دوري؟
You seem exhausted, so you're scheduled to be last.
تبدين مرهقة، لذا ترتيبك الأخير
In that case, I think I'll go wash my face in the ladies' room.
سأذهب لغسل وجهي في دورة مياه السيدات قبل ذلك إذاً
How many more interviewees are there?
كم استجواباً بقي لديكم؟
Including Dr. Narumi, there's six--
بإضافة الطبيبة نارومي يكونون ستّة
the mayor's daughter, Reiko Kuroiwa,
ابنة العمدة هناك، كوريوا ريكو
her fiancé, Shuichi Murasawa,
وخطيبها موراساوا شويتشي
mayoral candidate, Masato Shimizu,
المرشّح للعمدة شيميزو ماساتو
the mayor's secretary, Kazuaki Hirata,
وسكرتير العمدة هيراتا كازواكي
and Ken Nishimoto, who we're interviewing right now,
ونيشيموتو كين الذي نستجوبه حالياً
but he's really wasting our time.
لكنه يهدر وقتنا حقاً
He won't say a word, no matter what we ask him.
لا ينبس ببنت شفة مهما سألناه
My instincts say he did it!
تخبرني غريزتي أنّه كان الفاعل
Idiot! There's no curse on the piano!
!أحمق! أي لعنة بيانو تتحدث عنها؟
As long as that thing's around, these murders will keep happening!
تحصل هذه الجرائم باستمرار لوجود ذاك الشيء
But, Mayor...
...لكن أيّها العمدة
Dispose of it immediately! You hear me, Hirata?!
!تخلّص منه فوراً! واضح يا هيراتا؟
Y-Yes, sir!
!حـ-حاضر
Give me a break!
...تبّاً
I've had enough of this!
!يكفي هذا
I have no motive for killing Kawashima-san!
!لا دافع لديّ لقتل كاواشيما-سان
Ugh!
!يا إلهي
Wow, listen to Reiko-san go.
اسمعي لريكو-سان
She's been shouting for 10 minutes straight.
لم تتوقف عن الصراخ لعشر دقائق
That's strange.
هذا غريب
They're through questioning him, so why isn't Nishimoto-san leaving?
انتهوا من استجوابه، فلمَ لم يغادر نيشيموتو-سان؟
Huh?
ماذا؟
I need to go to the bathroom.
سـ-سأذهب لدورة المياه
Huh? Did Nishimoto-san come in here just now?
ماذا؟ ألم يدخل نيشيموتو-سان هنا للتو؟
No.
كلا
Crap! He took the stairs!
!تبّاً! صعد الأدراج
This music...
...هذه المقطوعة
It's the second movement of Moonlight...
...إنّها الحركة الثانية لضوء القمر
Where's it coming from?!
!أين مصدر الصوت؟
The broadcast room!
!غرفة البثّ
Nishimoto-san!
!نيشيموتو-سان
Too late!
!تبّاً
No, don't go inside!
!كلا، لا تدخلي
Get the examiners and autopsy team here at once!
!استدعوا المحلّلين وفريق التشريح فوراً
Inspector.
حضرة المفتش
The autopsy team left for Tokyo this evening to work on Kawashima-san.
غادر فريق التشريح لطوكيو مساءً لفحص جثّة كاواشيما-سان
What?!
!ماذا؟
Damn it! Now, of all times!
...تبّاً! في هذا الوقت
Um...
المعذرة
I can do it...
يمكنني فعلها
Dr. Narumi...
...الطبيبة نارومي
But now this narrows down the suspects to a handful of people!
لكن هذا يقلّص عدد المشتبه بهم لفئة محدودة
So the killer is still--
...لا يزال القاتل إذاً
All the exits to this building are guarded by police.
تحرس الشرطة كافة مخارج هذا المبنى
Damn it!
!تبّاً
Who is it? Who's the killer?!
!من هو؟! من القاتل؟
It appears only a few minutes have passed since the victim's death.
يبدو أنّه مضت بضع دقائق فقط على موت الضحية
Yes, the first 5 minutes and 30 seconds of this tape seem to be blank.
بالفعل، يبدو أنّ أول خمس دقائق ونصف لهذا الشريط فارغة
Inspector Megure!
!المفتّش ميغوري
There was something strange beneath the body!
!كان هناك شيءٌ غريب أسفل الجثة
What?!
!ماذا؟
Sheet music?
قطعة موسيقية؟
Is this another dying message from the victim?
أهذه رسالة احتضار أخرى من الضحية؟
No.
كلا
If he had the time and strength to write all this with his own blood,
،لو كان لديه وقت وقوّة لكتابة كلّ هذا بدمه
he would've called for help instead.
لطلب المساعدة
The killer probably left each of these behind to--
...ترك القاتل هذه غالباً
Oh no! That's important evidence!
!كلا! الدليل الثمين
It's okay!
!إنّه بخير
You're in the way! Get out of here!
!أنت تعترض عملنا! اخرج
Seeing as Beethoven's Moonlight Sonata was played after each murder,
بما أنّ سوناتا ضوء القمر لبيتهوفين عُزفت ،بعد كلّ جريمة قتل
it would seem the same person killed Kawashima-san and Kuroiwa-san.
يمكننا استنتاج أنّ قاتل كاواشيما-سان في الجريمة الأولى وقاتل كوريوا-سان في الثانية هو الشخص نفسه
And judging from the amount of blank tape,
،وبناءً على جزء الشريط الفارغ
Kuroiwa-san must have been killed
قُتل كوريوا-سان
around 6:30, only minutes before he was found.
عند السادسة ونصف، قبل دقائق فقط من اكتشاف جثته
In other words, the killer must have been one of you,
أي أنّ القاتل أحدكم بما أنّكم
since you were the only ones in the community center at the time!
!كنتم الوحيدين في المركز الاجتماعي في هذا الوقت
Excluding Mori-kun and the others,
،باستثناء موري-كن والبقية
that leaves us with Ken Nishimoto-san, who was the first to find him,
يبقى المكتشف الأول للجثة، نيشيموتو كين-سان
Dr. Narumi Asai, who was kind enough to inspect the body for us just now,
والطبيبة أساي نارومي التي تفضّلت بتشريح الجثة
Kazuaki Hirata-san, secretary to the late Mayor Kuroiwa,
وهيراتا كازواكي-سان، سكرتير العمدة كوريوا المتوفى
Mayor Kuroiwa's daughter, Reiko Kuroiwa-san
وابنة العمدة، كوريوا ريكو-سان
and her fiancé, Shuichi Murasawa-san.
وخطيبها موراساوا شويتشي-سان
And then Masato Shimizu-san, candidate in the mayoral election.
وأخيراً شيميزو ماساتو-سان، المرشح في انتخابات العمدة
Hold on! Why am I a suspect?!
!انتظر! لمَ أنا ضمن المشتبه بهم؟
You've been questioning me since 6:20!
!كنتَ تستجوبني منذ السادسة والثلث
You're right, you couldn't have done it...
...معك حق، لم يكن بإمكانك ارتكاب الجريمة
Then you can exclude Dr. Narumi too!
يمكنكم استثناء الطبيبة نارومي أيضاً إذاً
She's been with us since 6:00.
فقد كانت رفقتنا مذ تمام السادسة
Right, Conan-kun?
صحيح يا كونان-كن؟
Yeah!
أجل
So that leaves the four men as the only suspects...
يبقى أربعة رجال مشتبه بهم إذاً
Excuse me, but I've been on this floor since 6:00 or so...
المعذرة، لكني كنت على هذا الطابق منذ السادسة
Do you have anyone to substantiate this?
ألديك شاهد؟
You can all vouch for me, right?
يمكنكم أن تشهدوا بوجودي، صحيح؟
Sorry, but I went to the restroom around 6:30.
آسف، لكني ذهبت لدورة المياه عند السادسة والنصف
You were the first person to find Kuroiwa-san...
كنتَ أوّل من وجد جثّة كوريوا-سان
What exactly were you doing there?
ماذا كنت تفعل هناك؟
Kuroiwa said he wanted to see me.
قال كوريوا أنّه يريد رؤيتي
Are you sure you didn't ask to see him so you could kill him?!
!ألم تكن من استدعاه وقتله؟
No!
!كـ-كلا
It was Shimizu!
!كان شيميزو
With Kawashima and my father taken out of the election,
،باختفاء كاواشيما وأبي من الانتخابات
he'd automatically wind up in the mayor's seat!
!سيفوز بمنصب العمدة تلقائياً
Oh? What are you looking at, Conan-kun?
ماذا؟ ما الذي تنظر له يا كونان-كن؟
Don't be stupid!
لا تكوني حمقاء! لن أقتلهما الاثنين !لأخذ منصب العمدة فقط
The sheet music the killer left at the murder scene.
القطعة الموسيقية التي تركها القاتل في مسرح الجريمة
My guess is that it's a coded message from the murderer.
أظنّها رسالة مشفرة من القاتل
I wonder if there's anything special about these sharps and flats...
أتساءل إن كان هناك شيء مميز في هذه النغمات الحادة والمنخفضة
Those are the black keys on the keyboard. You know?
هذه المفاتيح السوداء على لوحة المفاتيح، صحيح؟
Keyboard?
لوحة المفاتيح؟
Arrest this homicidal maniac before he kills anyone else--
...اعتقلوا هذا القاتل فوراً! وإلّا سيموت المزيد
Better watch out. You're next.
احترس، دورك التالي
Conan-kun?
كونان-كن؟
This code's easy if you know how to read it.
هذه الشفرة سهلة إن عرفتِ كيف تقرئينها
It's based on the notes that correspond with specific piano keys
إنها مبنية على النغمات المتوافقة مع مفاتيح بيانو محددة
if you arrange the letters of the alphabet across a piano keyboard.
.إن رتبت أحرف الأبجدية على لوحة مفاتيح بيانو
Using this, the music found where Kawashima-san was killed says,
باستعمال هذا، تقول القطعة الموسيقية :حيث قُتل كاواشيما-سان
"Better watch out. You're next."
"احترس، دورك التالي"
See?
هكذا
You're amazing, Conan-kun!
!مذهل يا كونان-كن
What does the other sheet music say?!
!ماذا تقول القطعة الموسيقية الأخرى إذاً؟
Let's see...
...حسناً
"Extinguished is the anger of the hellfire."
"غضب نار الجحيم مُطفأ"
The anger of the hellfire?! Could it be...
...غضب نار الجحيم؟! أيمكن
...that pianist who killed himself in a fire 12 years ago?!
عازف البيانو الذي انتحر في حريق قبل 12 عاماً؟
It's him! Keiji Aso's alive!
!إنّه هو! أسو كيجي حيّ
No he isn't.
ليس هو
The bones found in the ashes matched his dental records--
آثار العظام التي وجدناها في الرماد وافقت سجّل أسنانه
he's most certainly dead.
لا شكّ أنه ميت
Everything was completely scorched.
كان كلّ شيء محروقاً تماماً
All that was left was some sheet music in a fireproof safe.
ما تبقى كانت قطعةً موسيقية في خزنة مضادة للحرائق فقط
Sheet music?!
!قطعة موسيقية؟
Where? Where is this sheet music?!
!أين هي؟ أين تلك القطعة الموسيقية؟
In the community center storeroom.
في مخزن المركز الاجتماعي
But the key to the storeroom's back at the station--
...لكن مفتاح المخزن في المحطة
Then go get it!
!اذهب واجلبه إذاً
Alright!
!حاضر
Wait, Officer! I'm coming too!
!انتظر أيّها الضابط! سأرافقك
Conan-kun!
!كونان-كن
Say, did Aso-san really set his own house on fire?
أخبرني، هل أحرق أسو-سان منزله حقاً؟
Yes, there were four eyewitnesses.
أجل، كان هناك أربعة شهود
Our previous mayor, Kameyama-san,
العمدة السابق كامياما-سان
Mayor Kuroiwa, Nishimoto-san, and Kawashima-san.
والعمدة كوريوا ونيشيموتو-سان وكاواشيما-سان
Were those four connected in any way?
أكانت هناك صلة بينهم؟
They were all classmates, including Aso-san.
كانوا زملاء دراسة جميعاً، بالإضافة لأسو-سان
Then what about that Murasawa guy?
ماذا عن موراساوا ذاك إذاً؟
He showed up on the island 3 years ago.
ظهر على تلك الجزيرة قبل 3 أعوام
He and the mayor's daughter Reiko-san were engaged not too long ago.
خطب ابنة العمدة ريكو-سان قبل فترة قصيرة
The mayor opposed it, though.
مع أنّ العمدة عارض ذلك
What about Hirata, the mayor's secretary?
ماذا عن سكرتير العمدة، هيراتا؟
He's suspicious if you ask me.
ذاك الشخص مثير للشبهة
I'm not quite sure what the deal was,
لا أعرف ما قصته بالضبط
but he was always sneaking around with Kawashima-san
لكنه كان يتسلل مع كاواشيما-سان
at the community center.
في المركز الاجتماعي دوماً
What about Shimizu?
ماذا عن شيميزو؟
He has a strong sense of justice and he's very popular with the fishermen!
لديه حسّ قوي بالعدالة، ويملك شعبية كبيرة بين الصيادين
Are you out of questions, Akechi-kun?
هل انتهت أسئلتك يا أكيتشي-كن؟
Huh? That's odd!
!ماذا؟ هذا غريب
I could swear it was around here somewhere...
...كان هنا حتماً
Come on. You've been looking for over an hour now.
يا إلهي، مضت ساعة وأنت تبحث
Here we go! Here's the key!
!ها هو! إنّه هذا المفتاح
Officer!
!أيّها الضابط
Ran...?
ران-نيتشان
You took too long!
!تأخّرتما
Everyone grew tired of waiting so they went home!
سئم الجميع من الانتظار وغادروا
All the suspects left?!
!غادر كلّ المشتبه بهم؟
Yeah.
أجل
The killer's last message said that the hellfire's anger was extinguished,
قالت رسالة القاتل الأخيرة أنّ غضب نار الجحيم قد انطفأ
so they figured there would be no more murders.
لذا ظنّوا أنه لن تقع المزيد من الجرائم
Idiots!
!لا يمكن
Only the 1st and 2nd movements of Moonlight have been played
عُزفت أول حركتين فقط لضوء القمر
at each of the murder scenes so far!
!في مسرح كلّ جريمة حتى الآن
Moonlight has one movement left!
!تبقى لضوء القمر حركة أخيرة
I'm going to check out the community center!
!سأذهب لتفقد المركز الاجتماعي
Wait! Conan-kun!
!انتظر! كونان-كن
Talk about curious, Conan-kun...
يا لفضولك يا كونان-كن
Hurry!
!أسرع وافتحه
Just hold on, will you?
انتظر قليلاً
Did you just hear a strange sound come from the piano room?
ألم تسمعا صوتاً غريباً من غرفة البيانو؟
No...
كلا
Conan-kun!
!كونان-كن
Stop!
!انتظر
Murasawa-san!
!موراساوا-سان
Ran!
!ران
The storeroom!
!المخزن
Officer! Go call Inspector Megure!
!حضرة الضابط، اتّصل بالمفتش ميغوري
I'm on it!
!حسناً
Was the 3rd movement played?
هل عُزفت الحركة الثالثة؟
There's 30 minutes per side on this tape,
توجد 30 دقيقة لكلّ جانب لهذا الشريط
which means Nishimoto-san died within the last 30 minutes!
مما يعني أنّ نيشيموتو-سان مات خلال النصف ساعة الماضية
Look, Conan-kun!
!انظر يا كونان-كن
There's some more sheet music at Nishimoto-san's feet!
!توجد قطعة موسيقية أخرى عند أقدام نيشيموتو-سان
What does it say this time?
ما تقول هذه المرة؟
"Will."
"وصيّة"
It's his will?!
وصيّته؟
Then does that mean...
...إذاً
It was a suicide?
كان انتحاراً؟
According to the will,
،وفقاً للوصيّة
he regretted killing Mr. Kawashima and Mr. Kuroiwa...
فقد شعر بالندم على قتل السيّد كاواشيما والسيّد كوريوا
Nishimoto killed the two of them?!
!نيشيموتو من قتلهما؟
He apparently didn't want an old mistake they made to be made known.
يبدو أنّه لم يرد أن يُكشف خطأ قديم ارتكبوه
"They" refers to Mr. Kameyama, who died 2 years ago,
والمشار لهم هم السيّد كامياما الذي مات قبل عامين
Mr. Kawashima and Mr. Kuroiwa, who were just killed,
والسيّد كاواشيما والسيّد كوريوا اللذان ماتا مؤخراً
Mr. Nishimoto, who hanged himself,
والسيّد نيشيموتو الذي شنق نفسه
and Mr. Aso, who killed himself 12 years ago.
وأخيراً السيّد أسو الذي انتحر قبل 12 عاماً
The pianist too?
عازف البيانو أيضاً؟
My guess is that they did something, using this code.
أتوقع أنّهم قاموا بشيء باستعمال هذه الشفرة
I see. Nishimoto-san was afraid their old secret would get out
هكذا إذاً، كان نيشيموتو يخشى فضح سرّهم القديم
so he broke into the storeroom to destroy the sheet music.
فاقتحم المخزن للتخلص من القطعة الموسيقية
But unable to find the music and driven into a psychological corner,
،لكن عجزه عن العثور عليها حاصره نفسياً
he committed suicide.
فقام بالانتحار
I don't think it was a suicide.
لا أظنّه كان انتحاراً
It's impossible to hang yourself without something to support you, right?
من المُحال أن تشنق نفسك دون ما يسندك تحتك، صحيح؟
Are you sure you didn't put it away?
ألم تكن أنت من أبعده؟
Of course not.
لم أفعل ذلك
And I doubt there's anyone who would go and write their own will in code.
كما أشك أن يكتب أحدهم وصيته باستخدام شفرة
Are you saying the murderer is somewhere else?
أتقصد أنّ القاتل شخص آخر؟
I saw some suspicious people.
رأيتُ شخصاً مريباً
What?!
!ماذا؟
Two people in the piano room.
اثنان في غرفة البيانو
One broke a window and escaped.
أحدهما حطّم النافذة وهرب
The other was that Murasawa guy.
بينما الآخر كان موراساوا-نيتشان
Someone beat him up.
ضربه أحدهم
Dr. Narumi's treating him in the piano room right now.
وتعالجه الطبيبة نارومي في غرفة البيانو الآن
Why didn't you say that sooner?!
!لمَ لم تقل ذلك قبلاً؟
Dad!
!أبي
You still haven't found Mr. Aso's sheet music?!
لم تجد قطعة السيّد أسو الموسيقية بعد؟
It was 12 years ago. There's no way for me to remember where we put it.
حدث ذلك قبل 12 عاماً، من المستحيل أن أتذكر أين وضعناها
Is he still unconscious?
لا يزال فاقداً للوعي؟
Yes. I think he may have suffered a concussion.
أجل، أظنّه تلقى ارتجاجاً دماغياً
Say, Kuroiwa-san.
بالمناسبة يا كوريوا-سان
What was Murasawa-san doing here this late anyway?
ما الذي كان يفعله موراساوا-سان هنا في هذا الوقت المتأخر؟
How should I know?!
!كيف لي أن أعرف؟
This is a...
...هـ-هذا
Keep your hands off Shuichi's stuff!
!لا تلمس أغراض شويتشي
What is that?
ما ذاك الشيء؟
Don't ask me! But it was important to Shuichi!
!لا أدري! لكنه كان مهماً لشويتشي
That's a tuning hammer, used to tune pianos.
إنّها مطرقة تنغيم تُستعمل لضبط البيانو
So he was the one who...
...أي أنه كان من
Okay! Bring all the suspects to the town hall at once!
حسنٌ، اجلبوا كافة المشتبه بهم لدار البلدية فوراً
Yes, sir!
!حاضر
What are you doing, Conan-kun?
ما الذي تفعله يا كونان-كن؟
Let's go to the town hall.
سنذهب لدار البلدية
The suspicious person who ran out of this room
كان الشخص المريب الذي هرب من هذه الغرفة يبحث
was looking for something under the piano.
عن شيءٍ أسفل البيانو
Here we are!
!هنا! وجدته
Wow, a hidden panel! Cool!
!مُذهل، لوح خفيّ! رائع
Drugs!
!مخدرات
Tsukikage Island Town Hall
دار  بلدية جزيرة تسوكيكاغي
Judging from the methods employed in all three murders,
بناءً على أساليب الحوادث الثلاثة ،التي وقعت على هذه الجزيرة
they are all clearly the work of the same person!
فالفاعل هو نفس الشخص بلا شك
and are no longer suspects.
فخرجا عن لائحة المشتبه بهم
But there are no alibis for the secretary Hirata-san,
لكن لا حجّة غياب هناك للسكرتير هيراتا-سان
the mayoral candidate Shimizu-san,
والمرشح للعمدة شيميزو-سان
nor for Murasawa-san, who is currently resting at the clinic...
ولا لموراساوا-سان الذي يرقد في عيادة حالياً
The killer is one of these three!
!القاتل أحد هؤلاء الثلاثة
Dr. Narumi. Is Murasawa-san still unconscious?
طبيبة نارومي، لا يزال موراساوا-سان فاقداً للوعي؟
Yes. Reiko-san is looking after him, but he has yet to regain consciousness.
أجل، ريكو-سان تعتني به لكنه لم يستعد وعيه بعد
There's something nagging at me, but what could it be?!
هناك شيءٌ يضايقني، لكن ما هو؟
Ever since I saw the code of blood left at the scene of the crime...
...مُذ رأيت شفرة الدم في مسرح الجريمة
Inspector.
حضرة المفتش
The photos taken from where Mr. Kuroiwa was murdered are ready!
صور مسرح جريمة قتل السيّد كوريوا جاهزة
Good. Place them on that desk.
حسنٌ، ضعها على تلك الطاولة
Yes, sir!
حاضر
What's that light by Kuroiwa-san's neck?
ما هذا الضوء عند عنق السيّد كوريوا؟
It's off in the picture where he's been moved.
ليس موجوداً في الصورة بعد تحريكه
Um, may I buy some juice? I'm thirsty...
أيمكنني الذهاب لشراء عصير؟ أشعر بالعطش
I suppose that'd be alright.
لا مشكلة
He's injured?
مُصاب؟
Say, Mister.
يا عمّ
There's some white powder on your sleeves.
يوجد مسحوق أبيض على كمّيك
What?!
!ماذا؟
Money from all over the world!
!نقود كثيرة من كلّ أرجاء العالم
I'm fond of foreign countries.
أُحب البلدان الأجنبية
Huh?
ماذا؟
What's wrong, Officer?
ما الخطب أيّها الشرطي؟
I finally found the sheet music Aso-san left behind!
وجدتُ أخيراً القطعة الموسيقية !التي تركها أسو-سان
Let me see that!
!دعني أرى
"To my son, Seiji."
"و ا غام وسو كو س ي جي إيه"
Son?
ا-ابن؟
Oh, come to think of it, Aso-san had a son too...
...صحيح، كان لأسو سان ابن أيضاً
He fell seriously ill when he was little and had to be hospitalized...
أصابه مرض شديد في صغره وتمّ إسعافه للمشفى
I believe Seiji was his name...
أظنّ اسمه كان سيجي
Seiji?!
!سيجي؟
It couldn't be!
...لا-لا يمكن
Hey, wait! Where do you think you're going?!
!أنت! انتظر أيّها الصبي! أين تذهب؟
Ah, now I see!
!هكذا إذاً! فهمت
The reason the killer dragged Kawashima-san into the piano room
سبب استدراج القاتل كاواشيما-سان لغرفة البيانو
after drowning him!
!بعد إغراقه له
The meaning of the music played at the murder scenes!
ومعنى المعزوفة التي شُغلت في مسارح الجريمة
And the mystery behind the code written in blood!
ولغز الشفرة المكتوبة بالدم
There's no doubt about it! That's the one who did it!
!لا شكّ في الأمر، ذاك الشخص هو المجرم
Mr. Mori received a letter from a dead man
تلقّى العم موري رسالةً من رجل مُتوفى
and then headed to Tsukikage Island.
وتوجه لجزيرة تسوكيكاغي
The letter's author was Keiji Aso, a pianist who murdered his family,
كان المُرسل أسو كيجي، عازف بيانو قتل عائلته
lit his house on fire, and died while playing the Moonlight piano sonata.
وأحرق منزله ومات وهو يعزف سوناتا بيانو ضوء القمر
The 1st murder happened on the night of the memorial for Mr. Kameyama,
وقعت أوّل جريمة في ليلة ذكرى العمدة السابق
the previous mayor.
السيّد كامياما
Hideo Kawashima was found dead in the piano room,
وُجد كاواشيما هيديو ميتاً في غرفة البيانو
while the first movement of Moonlight played.
مع تسجيل عزف الحركة الأولى لضوء القمر
The second murder took place as the second movement played.
ووقعت الجريمة الثانية مع تسجيل الحركة الثانية
The victim was the current mayor, Tatsuji Kuroiwa.
كان الضحية العمدة الحالي كوريوا تاتسوجي
The number of suspects was narrowed down to six people.
وتقلّص عدد المشتبه بهم إلى ستّة أشخاص
The third murder was that of Ken Nishimoto.
وضحيّة الجريمة الثالثة كان نيشيموتو كين
He was killed in a manner that made it look like suicide.
الذي قُتل بأسلوب يجعله يبدو انتحاراً
"To my son, Seiji."
"إلى ابني سيجي"
Ah, now I see!
!هكذا إذاً! فهمت
The reason the killer dragged Kawashima-san into the piano room
سبب استدراج القاتل لكاواشيما-سان لغرفة البيانو
after drowning him!
!بعد إغراقه له
The meaning of the music played at the murder scenes!
ومعنى المعزوفة التي شُغلت في مسارح الجريمة
And the mystery behind the code written in blood!
ولغز الشفرة المكتوبة بالدم
There's no doubt about it! That's the one who did it!
!لا شكّ في الأمر، ذاك الشخص هو المجرم
What's the big idea, rushing here to the broadcast room like that?!
يا إلهي، لمَ ركضت لغرفة البثّ هكذا فجأةً؟
Is there something here?!
!أيوجد شيء هنا؟
No, not really.
كلا، ليس تماماً
I've got no choice! I'll have to use the old man's voice for this!
لا خيار لديّ، عليّ استعمال صوت العمّ وحلّ القضية
One shot of this Anesthetic Watch Gun and...
بطلقة واحدة من مسدّس الساعة المخدّر
Hirata-san and Shimizu-san will have to come to the mainland with us
سيرافقنا هيراتا-سان وشيميزو-سان لليابسة
tomorrow morning.
صباح الغد
You can't be serious!
!لـ-لكن
The first incident, in which Mr. Kawashima was drowned
الحادثة الأولى حيث أُغرق السيّد كاواشيما
and dragged into the community center's piano room last night...
وسُحبت جثته لغرفة بيانو المركز الاجتماعي ليلة الأمس
The second incident, in which Mr. Kuroiwa was murdered
والحادثة الثانية حيث قُتل السيّد كوريوا
in the broadcast room this very night...
في غرفة البثّ هذه الليلة
The third incident, which also took place this very night,
والحادثة الثالثة التي وقعت الليلة نفسها
in which Mr. Nishimoto was killed in the storeroom
حيث قُتل السيّد نيشيموتو في المخزن
in such a way to make it look like a suicide...
بأسلوب يجعله يبدو انتحاراً
The only ones without alibis for these three incidents are you two
أنتما الوحيدان اللذان لا يملكان حجّة غياب لهذه الحوادث الثلاث
and Murasawa-san, who is resting at the clinic.
بالإضافة لموراساوا-سان الذي يرقد في العيادة
I'm sorry to do this, but we'll have to watch you tonight.
يؤسفني فعل ذلك، لكن علينا حراستكم اليوم
I've figured it out, Inspector!
!حللتُ الأمر سيّدي المفتش
Almost everything about the murders on this island, that is.
كلّ ما يحيط بجرائم القتل على هذه الجزيرة
Dad! You're in the broadcast room?
أبي! أنت في غرفة البثّ؟
First, the person who beat Murasawa-san unconscious in the piano room.
بدايةً، الشخص الذي أفقد موراساوا-سان وعيه في غرفة البيانو
That would be you, Hirata-san!
ذاك أنت يا هيراتا-سان
What?!
!ماذا؟
Hirata-san suffered the injury on his left hand
أُصيبت يد هيراتا-سان اليسرى
when he broke the window and escaped.
عندما حطّم النافذة وهرب
You were also the suspicious person we saw last night.
كنتَ الشخص المشبوه الذي رأيناه ليلة الأمس أيضاً
But what was he doing?
لكن ما الذي كان يفعله؟
He was making deals with Mr. Kawashima in that room.
كان يعقد صفقات مع السيّد كاواشيما في تلك الغرفة
Drug deals.
صفقات مخدرات
Drugs?!
!مـ-مخدرات؟
Hirata-san used a hidden panel in the piano
استعمل هيراتا-سان لوحاً مخفياً في البيانو
to trade drugs he bought overseas for large sums of money.
للمتاجرة بمخدرات اشتراها خارج البلاد مقابل كمية كبيرة من النقود
Aha! So that's why they were at the community center every single night!
!هكذا إذاً! لذا كانا في المركز الاجتماعي كلّ ليلة
The reason Hirata-san always claimed the piano was cursed
سبب ادّعاء هيراتا-سان الدائم أنّ البيانو ملعون
was to keep people from getting in the way.
هو لإبعاد الناس من طريق صفقاته
He probably assaulted Murasawa-san and escaped
اعتدى على موراساوا-سان وهرب
because Murasawa-san saw him taking back the drugs he had left there!
لأنّه رآه يأخذ المخدرات التي تركها هناك غالباً
Does that mean you killed Mr. Kawashima
أي أنّك قتلت السيّد كاواشيما
because you were having a dispute with him about the deals?!
!لأنّكما تشاجرتما بشأن الصفقات؟
No!
!كـ-كلا
Hirata-san has nothing to do with the three murders.
لا علاقة لهيراتا-سان بالجرائم الثلاث
If he was the murderer, he wouldn't have killed anyone in the piano room.
لو كان القاتل، فلم يكن ليرتكب جرائمه في غرفة البيانو
That was the room where he left the drugs, after all.
فهي الغرفة التي خزّن المخدرات فيها
Next is Murasawa-san.
التالي هو موراساوا-سان
He's the killer?!
!هو القاتل؟
He's not the killer either.
ليس القاتل أيضاً
The reason the killer wrote a will to make it look a suicide
سبب كتابة القاتل وصيّةً لجعل الأمر يبدو انتحاراً
but didn't place an object to stand on in the room
وعدم وضعه لمسند أقدام في الغرفة
was because the murderer bolted when Ran and the others showed up.
هو هلعه عندما أتت ران والبقية ولوذه بالفرار
It would have been impossible to enter the piano room afterward.
سيكون من المستحيل دخول غرفة البيانو بعدها
You're right!
مـ-معك حق
So far, our image of the killer has been that of a man,
حتّى الآن، صورتنا عن القاتل هي رجل
because all three murders required someone with strength.
لأنّ الجرائم الثلاث تطلبت قوّةً بدنية
And someone without an alibi.
كما شخص دون حجّة غياب
The only suspect left is Shimizu-san...
المشتبه الوحيد المتبقي هو شيميزو-سان
Next, we need to look at the second murder.
الآن علينا إمعان النظر في الجريمة الثانية
We assumed Kuroiwa-san was killed only minutes before he was found.
افترضنا أنّ كوريوا-سان قُتل قبيل دقائق من العثور على جثته
But if you'll remember...
...لكن تذكروا
...the blood code didn't come off when Conan fell on it.
لم تزل شفرة الدم عندما سقط كونان عليها آنذاك
At room temperature, it takes 15 to 30 minutes for human blood to dry.
يستغرق دم الإنسان 15 إلى 30 دقيقة ليجفّ في درجة حرارة الغرفة
But that blood was dry,
لكن كان ذاك الدم جافاً
even though he was supposedly killed only minutes before.
رغم أنّه قُتل قبيل دقائق افتراضياً
That's right. It was a trick the killer did to alter the estimated time of death.
صحيح، كانت حيلة استعملها المجرم للتلاعب بوقت الوفاة المقدر
What?!
!ما-ماذا؟
But only the first 5 and a half minutes of the tape were blank!
لكن كانت أوّل خمس دقائق ونصف هي الفارغة فقط في التسجيل
Automatic tape reverse.
قلب الشريط الآلي
The killer played the 2nd side of the tape, which had no music on it
شغّل القاتل الجانب الثاني للشريط الذي لم يحتو عزفاً
and gained 30 extra minutes by using tape reverse.
وحصل على 30 دقيقة إضافية باستعمال القلب الآلي
Please have a look at the photographs.
انظروا للصور رجاءً
There's a button lit near Kuroiwa-san's neck.
يوجد مفتاح مُضاء قرب عنق كوريوا-سان
And the light is off just after his body is moved.
لكن الضوء اختفى بعدما حُركت جثته
That's proof that the killer turned it off when you weren't looking.
هذا دليل على أنّ القاتل أطفأه بعيداً عن أنظار الشرطة
But if I remember correctly, the one who approached the body was--
...لكن وفقما أتذكر، من اقترب من الجثة آنذاك
That's right.
صحيح
The person who got near the body, aside from the police...
الشخص الوحيد الذي اقترب من الجثّة مع الشرطة
The person who faked the estimated time of death...
ومن زيّف وقت الوفاة المقدر
...was the one who inspected the body--you, Dr. Narumi!
...هو من فحص الجثة
That's not true, is it, Dr. Narumi?!
!هذا ليس صحيحاً، أليس كذلك أيّتها الطبيبة نارومي؟
You drowned Kawashima-san and dragged him into the piano room
أغرقتِ كاواشيما-سان وسحبته لغرفة البيانو
in order to send the coroners back to the mainland,
لإعادة محقّقي الوفاة لليابسة
since they wouldn't be able to examine an unnatural death here.
بما أنّهم لن يتمكنوا من تحليل موت غير طبيعي هنا
And the reason you put blank space at the start of each tape
وسبب وضعك للمساحة الفارغة في بداية كلّ تسجيل
was so that you could throw us off by faking the time of the 2nd murder.
هو كي تستطيعي تضليلنا بتزييف وقت الجريمة الثانية
Doing this, you altered Kuroiwa-san's time of death,
وهكذا، تلاعبتِ بوقت موت كوريوا-سان
thereby creating an alibi for yourself.
وصنعتِ حجّة غياب لنفسك
But Mori-kun! You just said the killer was a man!
!لكن يا موري-كن، قلتَ أن المجرم رجل
The motive for the murders extends 12 years back.
دافع الجرائم يعود لاثني عشر عاماً مضى
Come again?
أتسمعني؟
Back to the incident in which pianist Keiji Aso and his family were killed.
لحادثة مقتل عازف البيانو أسو كيجي وعائلته
Killed?!
!مقتل؟
Kawashima-san, Nishimoto-san, Kuroiwa-san,
كاواشيما-سان ونيشيموتو-سان وكوريوا-سان
and the previous mayor, Kameyama-san...
والعمدة السابق كامياما-سان
They used Aso-san's international performances
استغلوا عروض عزف أسو-سان العالمية
as opportunities to buy and sell drugs.
كفرصة للمتاجرة بالمخدرات
But then Aso-san said he refused to help them any longer.
لكن قال أسو-سان عندها أنّه لن يتعاون معهم مجدداً
Afraid their secret would get out,
خشيةً من فضح سرّهم
they shut him and his family inside his house and set it on fire.
أغلقوا عليه وعائلته في منزلهم وأحرقوه
This is all written in the sheet music that survived that fire...
كلّ هذا مكتوب في القطعة الموسيقية التي نجت من النار
In the confession letter that Aso-san wrote for his child...
في رسالة الاعتراف التي كتبها أسو-سان لطفله
A son?!
!ابنه؟
He had a son in a Tokyo hospital.
كان لديه ابن في مشفى في طوكيو
One named Seiji.
اسمه سيجي
Seiji? It couldn't be...
...سيجي؟ أيمكن
Dr. Narumi's real name is Seiji.
اسم الطبيبة نارومي الحقيقي هو سيجي
She was Keiji Aso's son, Seiji Aso!
!كانت ابن أسو كيجي، أسو سيجي
You can't be serious!
!مـ-محال
Asai is probably his foster family's last name.
أساي هو اسم عائلته المتبناة غالباً
So it was all to avenge his father...
كان كلّ هذا انتقاماً لأبيه إذاً
Inspector! The killer's gone!
!سيدي المفتش! اختفى المجرم
Find him!
!ابحثوا عنه
I know where he is!
أعرف أين هو
The place where Aso Keiji's donated piano is kept--the community center!
المكان الذي يوجد فيه البيانو الذي تبرع به أسو كيجي، المركز الاجتماعي
It's over, Father.
انتهى الأمر يا أبي
It's not over yet!
!لم ينته بعد
Here, look at this!
!عليك إلقاء نظرة هنا
It's written in this sheet music your dad left for you!
هناك رسالة لك في القطعة الموسيقية التي تركها والدك
He says he wants you to live an honest life!
!يقول أنّه يريد منك عيش حياة صالحة
I wish I had known that sooner.
أتمنى لو عرفت ذلك أبكر
How did you find out about your father if you haven't read this?!
لم تقرأها؟ كيف عرفت ما حلّ بأبيك إذاً؟
I always had my suspicions about my foster father.
راودتني الشكوك باستمرار بشأن أبي بالتبني
After graduating from medical school,
،فبعد تخرجي من كلية الطب
I came to this island as a woman doctor.
أتيتُ لهذه الجزيرة كطبيبة
It doesn't say on my license how to pronounce my name, after all.
فنطق اسمي ليس مكتوباً على رخصتي الطبية
But I was sweating bullets when they started questioning people.
لكني كنت متوتراً عندما بدؤوا الاستجواب
They would've found out I was really a man.
كانوا ليكتشفوا أنّي ذكر
I see. So that's why you stayed with us that night--
هكذا إذاً، لذا بقيت معنا تلك الليلة
so you could have them question you last.
كي تؤجل استجوابك للنهاية
When I told Kameyama, the previous mayor, that I was Aso's son,
عندما أخبرت العمدة السابق كامياما أنّي ابن أسو
he suddenly grew fearful and told me everything.
هلع فجأةً وأفصح لي عن كلّ شيء
He finished it all off by falling lifeless from a heart attack.
وفارق الحياة بعدها بنوبة قلبية
It was when I played my father's favorite piece, Moonlight,
،وعندما عزفت مقطوعة أبي المفضلة، ضوء القمر كلحن وداع له
as a farewell song for him that I came up with the idea for these murders.
خطرت لي فكرة هذه الجرائم
Seiji! Let's get out of here! We can still make it!
!لنخرج يا سيجي-سان! لا يزال بإمكاننا النجاة
It's too late for me.
فات الأوان عليّ
These hands are as bloodstained as theirs are.
فيداي ملطّختان بالدم مثل أولئك الأربعة
Conan-kun!
!كونان-كن
Dammit!
!تبّاً
No!
!كلا
Let go!
!دعيني
What's that sound?
ما هذا الصوت؟
This is the code.
إنّها الشفرة
He's playing it. Inside the fire.
إنّه يعزف، بين ألسنة النار
Murasawa-san missed Keiji Aso, the pianist,
افتقد موراساوا-سان عازف البيانو أسو كيجي
so he apparently tuned his piano on occasion...
فكان يضبط البيانو خاصته من حين لآخر وفقما يبدو
On the night he was assaulted, too.
في ليلة تعرضه للاعتداء أيضاً
Why did Dr. Narumi warn us about the murders?
لمَ أرسل لنا الطبيب نارومي تحذيراً عن الجرائم؟
My only guess is that it was actually a letter of challenge to Dad...
ربما كانت رسالة تحدّي لأبي
I think she wanted to be stopped from killing...
أظنّه أراد أن يوقفه أحد عن القتل
Say, what did the code that Dr. Narumi played say?
أخبرني، ما تحليل الشفرة التي عزفها الطبيب نارومي؟
Oh, I already forgot.
نسيت ذلك
Your expression says otherwise!
!تعابيرك لا توحي بذلك
Thank you, Little Detective
شكراً لك أيّها المتحري الصغير
Don't tell me the car Ayumi-chan got in
أيمكن أنّ السيارة التي صعدتها أيومي-تشان
belonged to those kidnappers who're killing little girls!
!هي لمجرمي اختطاف الفتيات وقتلهن؟
Hold on, Ayumi-chan! We're coming to save you!
!انتظري يا أيومي-تشان! سنأتي لإنقاذك فوراً
On the next Conan--
في الحلقة القادمة من كونان
Ayumi-chan's Abduction.
اختطاف أيومي-تشان
Next Conan's Hint:
تلميح الحلقة القادمة
A School Festival.
مهرجان مدرسيّ